<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francisco Mora on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</title>
    <link>/authors/francisco-mora/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Francisco Mora on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/francisco-mora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Economic valuation of ecosystem services from secondary tropical forests: trade-offs and implications for policy making</title>
      <link>/publication/naime-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/naime-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Natural regeneration of secondary forests can be an important source of recovery of ecosystem services (ES) critical for humanity, especially for climate change mitigation and adaptation goals. However, natural regeneration entails synergies and trade-offs across ESs and across stakeholders. To evaluate these trade-offs, we assessed the economic value of four ESs along the course of a natural regeneration process of tropical dry forests of the Pacific Coast of Mexico, and examined how this can inform the design of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) schemes incentivizing forest restoration. We estimated the monetary value of two provisioning ESs –forest products and fodder for calves–, using contingent valuation and direct market valuation methods, and two regulating ESs –carbon stocks and carbon sinks– using the voluntary carbon market prices and the social cost of carbon. We assessed these ESs in four natural regeneration stages: pasture, young secondary forest (0 to 12 years of natural regeneration), intermediate secondary forest (between 12 and 25 years of natural regeneration), and old-growth forest (more than 25 years of natural regeneration or primary forests).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving the accuracy of aboveground biomass estimations in secondary tropical dry forests</title>
      <link>/publication/bojorquez-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bojorquez-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biomass estimates in tropical forests are mainly available for old-growth forests, but the expansion of tropical secondary forests urges the development of tools for more accurate estimations of biomass and carbon pools. In this study, we developed local allometric models to estimate aboveground biomass in secondary tropical dry forests of the Chamela region in western Mexico and compared their accuracy to that of non-local (“foreign”) allometric models. We harvested 303 trees from 27 woody species contributing ≥75% of total basal area in secondary forest plots (5–45 y-old) distributed across the landscape. Nine to 14 individuals per species, covering the full natural range in stem diameter (DBH) found in an inventory, were measured for DBH and height (H) before harvesting. Subsamples from each stem and branches were used for dry mass and wood specific density (WSD) determinations. Power model functions were fitted to relate tree AGB to one or a multiplicative combination of three predictors (DBH, H, and WSD). Species-specific models with DBH alone explained a high percentage of the variance in tree AGB (R2 = 0.927 to 0.999). Among our multispecies models, fit and prediction of biomass improved when pooling the species into low and high WSD functional groups. Using local or global WSD data did not affect the accuracy of our multispecies models. In contrast, bias increased in foreign models with the use of global WSD values. We discuss the applicability of our allometric models and foreign models to improve the accuracy of biomass predictions in secondary tropical dry forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling households’ natural resource management strategies: a case study in Jalisco, Mexico</title>
      <link>/publication/monroy-sais-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/monroy-sais-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The analysis of resource management strategies is considered to be relevant to the conservation and sustainable use of ecosystems. In Mexico, ejidos are the most important of the land tenure institutions that grant access to resources inside communities. Although it is recognized that an ejido’s internal structure creates different social groups, few studies have explored their resource management strategies. The aim of this study was to characterize natural resource management strategies in two ejidos in a highly biodiverse region on the southern coast of Jalisco, Mexico. We sought to identify differences in strategies and the variables that explain these differences. We took the household as the unit of analysis, and conducted 55 structured interviews that tackled different aspects of households’ productive activities and natural resource management. We used cluster and ordination analyses to generate a typology of natural resources management strategies, and linear models to identify the variables that differed among groups. The results show that four different natural resources management strategies were strongly associated with differences in land tenure and the type of ecosystem that a household manages. This information can help us to enhance and diversify strategies for sustaining both ecosystems and community livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the cascading effects of management and landscape on the arthropod guilds occurring in papaya plantations</title>
      <link>/publication/flores-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/flores-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arthropods can provide ecosystem services or disservices to agricultural systems. Whereas herbivores can cause substantial crop losses, natural enemies can offer pest regulation services that otherwise would be difficult to obtain. Two major factors affecting arthropod communities within plantations are farming practices and surrounding landscape. Previous studies have shown that natural enemies are less abundant in plantations within simplified landscapes and intense management practices, while herbivores do not always respond to these factors. Given the different roles of arthropods in plantations, we assessed the cascading effects that the surrounding landscape and different management practices can have on different arthropod guilds in papaya plantations, ultimately affecting plant damage and fruit production. A piecewise structural equation model was used to assess the direct and indirect effects of management practices and landscape upon herbivores and their natural enemies, and their cascading effects on papaya leaf damage and fruit production. We studied 11 papaya plantations in the surroundings of a tropical dry forest (TDF) in Jalisco, Mexico. The model indicated that there is a decrease of natural enemies with intensive conventional management, which had no effect on pest abundance. Furthermore, surrounding landscape had an effect on pest abundance and not on predators, but this effect was different between seasons. Even when pest abundance explained crop damage, this was not reflected on fruit production. Crop yield was explained by management practices, available phosphorus in soil and by the abundance of natural enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plant growth promotion traits of rhizosphere yeasts and their response to soil characteristics and crop cycle in maize agroecosystems</title>
      <link>/publication/sarabia-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/sarabia-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yeasts are common soil inhabitants, but information about their ecology is limited. Here we examined the abundance of rhizosphere yeasts in six conventional maize agroecosystems in two different geographic areas in Mexico differing in soil characteristics and agricultural practices. In order to examine the plant growth promotion potential of maize rhizosphere yeasts a collection of yeast species was obtained, which were identified taxonomically in terms of sequencing of the D1D2 domain. Main results showed that yeasts were present in all maize fields during the complete growing cycle, though highest during flowering. The abundance of rhizosphere yeasts responded negatively to soil pH and amount of Mg. The maize rhizosphere yeast collection obtained included eight species from six genera with the Ascomycota species Meyerozyma guillermondii and Candida railenensis as the most frequent. Four out of the eight yeast species solubilised Ca3(PO4)2, whereas none of the yeasts solubilised FePO4. Maize plant growth was promoted after inoculation with Cryptococcus flavus and Solicoccozyma aeria in terms of shoot dry weight and with C. railenensis in terms of root dry weight, but only in combination with mineral P fertilisation. In conclusion, rhizosphere yeasts with plant growth promotion traits are common in maize agroecosystems, where soil physico-chemical characteristics and plant growth stage seem to determine their abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizontal seed dispersal by dung beetles reduced seed and seedling clumping, but did not increase short-term seedling establishment</title>
      <link>/publication/urrea-galeano-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/urrea-galeano-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dung beetles are secondary seed dispersers, incidentally moving many of the seeds defecated by mammals vertically (seed burial) and/or horizontally as they process and relocate dung. Although several studies have quantified this ecological function of dung beetles, very few have followed seed fate until seedling establishment, and most of these have focused on the effects of seed burial. We know very little about the effects of horizontal seed movement by dung beetles, though it is generally assumed that it will affect plant recruitment positively through diminishing seed clumping. The objective of our study was to assess the effects of dung beetle activity on the spatial distribution of seeds and seedlings, and on the probability of seedling establishment. In a tropical rainforest in Mexico we carried out two complementary field experiments for each of two tree species (Bursera simaruba and Poulsenia armata), using seeds experimentally imbedded in pig dung and recording their fate and spatial location over time. For both species, dung beetle activity reduced the spatial clumping of seeds and seedlings; however, it did not increase the probability of seedling establishment. We discuss the context- and species-specificity of the combined effects of horizontal and vertical dispersal of seeds by dung beetles, and the need to quantify long-term seedling fates to more accurately determine the effects of seed movement by dung beetles on plant recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
