<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Silvia Margarita Carrillo-Saucedo on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</title>
    <link>/authors/silvia-margarita-carrillo-saucedo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Silvia Margarita Carrillo-Saucedo on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/silvia-margarita-carrillo-saucedo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Resilience of soil aggregation and exocellular enzymatic functions associated with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal communities along a successional gradient in a tropical dry forest</title>
      <link>/publication/carrillo-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/carrillo-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi are well-known contributors to soil aggregation and nutrient cycling functions, but we still know little about their capacity to resist or recover from persistent disturbance. Rangeland management may deteriorate these functions by affecting the activity of soil biota, including AM fungi, among other consequences. If affected, some soil properties show recovery when management stops and natural regeneration is allowed. We conducted an experiment to evaluate if the functions related to soil aggregation and promotion of exocellular enzymatic activities associated with AM fungal communities had been affected by rangeland management and, if they had, whether they recovered with successional time when management stopped. AM fungal communities from ten sites with different successional ages in a tropical dry forest region were inoculated to the same host growing in pots divided by mesh into a plant compartment and an AM mycelium compartment. We examined soil stable aggregates fractions and enzymatic activities produced or promoted by AM fungi. Soil aggregation changed significantly only after the study had run for 3 years, was higher in the hyphosphere than in the root compartment, and showed a low but positive relation with the successional age of the communities. The activity of phosphatase, but not casein-protease and beta-glucosidase, increased with successional age. Therefore, soil aggregation and enzyme activities associated with AM fungal communities seemed resilient because casein-protease and beta-glucosidase were unchanged, and aggregation and phosphatase were reduced by rangeland management but recovered with successional time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atributos funcionales de las comunidades de hongos micorrízicos arbusculares en parcelas en regeneración natural del bosque tropical seco</title>
      <link>/tesis/carrillo-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tesis/carrillo-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;doctorado-en-ciencias-biológicas-iies---unam&#34;&gt;Doctorado en Ciencias Biológicas, IIES - UNAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resumen&#34;&gt;Resumen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Los hongos micorrízicos arbusculares (HMA) son simbiontes de la mayoría de las plantas que incrementan la absorción de nutrientes del suelo y su transferencia a las plantas y promueven procesos como retención de agua, ciclaje de nutrientes y estabilidad en el suelo. No obstante, pocos estudios abordan sus respuestas a cambios ambientales y sus funciones en los ecosistemas al nivel de comunidad. Durante la regeneración del Bosque Tropical Seco (BTS) posterior al cambio de uso de suelo en la región de Chamela, Jalisco, se producen cambios en la vegetación y en las propiedades físicas y químicas del suelo que pueden afectar la estructura de las comunidades de organismos que lo habitan, como los HMA, y por ende, también sus funciones. El objetivo general de este trabajo fue entender las relaciones entre los cambios en la composición de especies de las comunidades de HMA durante la regeneración natural de un BTS y sus adaptaciones funcionales a través del análisis de algunos atributos funcionales. Se esperaba que los cambios ambientales durante la regeneración del BTS después del uso ganadero extensivo cambiaran la composición de especies y que esos cambios en composición alteraran los atributos funcionales y por tanto las funciones de las comunidades.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal spore communities of a tropical dry forest ecosystem show resilience to land-use change</title>
      <link>/publication/carrillo-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/carrillo-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We explored the resilience of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal (AMF) communities of a tropical dry forest ecosystem to land use as pastures. We compared spore community species richness, composition, abundance, and similarity between old-growth forests and active pastures, as a measure of resistance and examined the trajectory of change in successional fields when pasture use stopped to evaluate re- covery. Despite a few changes in species richness, community composition and structure were strikingly similar in all sites, including the active pastures. The spore communities were considered resistant to land use as pastures and showed minor changes along succession when management stopped. We found a significant negative relation between the frequency of Diversisporales and Glomerales indicating a selective species turnover driven mainly by the families Gigasporaceae and Glomeraceae. This was, however, unrelated to land use or successional time. These results suggest the AMF communities of this ecosystem seem resilient to management as pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
