<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Patricia Balvanera on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</title>
    <link>/authors/patricia-balvanera/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Patricia Balvanera on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/patricia-balvanera/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving the accuracy of aboveground biomass estimations in secondary tropical dry forests</title>
      <link>/publication/bojorquez-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bojorquez-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biomass estimates in tropical forests are mainly available for old-growth forests, but the expansion of tropical secondary forests urges the development of tools for more accurate estimations of biomass and carbon pools. In this study, we developed local allometric models to estimate aboveground biomass in secondary tropical dry forests of the Chamela region in western Mexico and compared their accuracy to that of non-local (“foreign”) allometric models. We harvested 303 trees from 27 woody species contributing ≥75% of total basal area in secondary forest plots (5–45 y-old) distributed across the landscape. Nine to 14 individuals per species, covering the full natural range in stem diameter (DBH) found in an inventory, were measured for DBH and height (H) before harvesting. Subsamples from each stem and branches were used for dry mass and wood specific density (WSD) determinations. Power model functions were fitted to relate tree AGB to one or a multiplicative combination of three predictors (DBH, H, and WSD). Species-specific models with DBH alone explained a high percentage of the variance in tree AGB (R2 = 0.927 to 0.999). Among our multispecies models, fit and prediction of biomass improved when pooling the species into low and high WSD functional groups. Using local or global WSD data did not affect the accuracy of our multispecies models. In contrast, bias increased in foreign models with the use of global WSD values. We discuss the applicability of our allometric models and foreign models to improve the accuracy of biomass predictions in secondary tropical dry forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Economic valuation of ecosystem services from secondary tropical forests: trade-offs and implications for policy making</title>
      <link>/publication/naime-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/naime-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Natural regeneration of secondary forests can be an important source of recovery of ecosystem services (ES) critical for humanity, especially for climate change mitigation and adaptation goals. However, natural regeneration entails synergies and trade-offs across ESs and across stakeholders. To evaluate these trade-offs, we assessed the economic value of four ESs along the course of a natural regeneration process of tropical dry forests of the Pacific Coast of Mexico, and examined how this can inform the design of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) schemes incentivizing forest restoration. We estimated the monetary value of two provisioning ESs –forest products and fodder for calves–, using contingent valuation and direct market valuation methods, and two regulating ESs –carbon stocks and carbon sinks– using the voluntary carbon market prices and the social cost of carbon. We assessed these ESs in four natural regeneration stages: pasture, young secondary forest (0 to 12 years of natural regeneration), intermediate secondary forest (between 12 and 25 years of natural regeneration), and old-growth forest (more than 25 years of natural regeneration or primary forests).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
