<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>management on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</title>
    <link>/tags/management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in management on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling households’ natural resource management strategies: a case study in Jalisco, Mexico</title>
      <link>/productos/monroy-sais-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/productos/monroy-sais-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The analysis of resource management strategies is considered to be relevant to the conservation and sustainable use of ecosystems. In Mexico, ejidos are the most important of the land tenure institutions that grant access to resources inside communities. Although it is recognized that an ejido’s internal structure creates different social groups, few studies have explored their resource management strategies. The aim of this study was to characterize natural resource management strategies in two ejidos in a highly biodiverse region on the southern coast of Jalisco, Mexico. We sought to identify differences in strategies and the variables that explain these differences. We took the household as the unit of analysis, and conducted 55 structured interviews that tackled different aspects of households’ productive activities and natural resource management. We used cluster and ordination analyses to generate a typology of natural resources management strategies, and linear models to identify the variables that differed among groups. The results show that four different natural resources management strategies were strongly associated with differences in land tenure and the type of ecosystem that a household manages. This information can help us to enhance and diversify strategies for sustaining both ecosystems and community livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the cascading effects of management and landscape on the arthropod guilds occurring in papaya plantations</title>
      <link>/productos/flores-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/productos/flores-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arthropods can provide ecosystem services or disservices to agricultural systems. Whereas herbivores can cause substantial crop losses, natural enemies can offer pest regulation services that otherwise would be difficult to obtain. Two major factors affecting arthropod communities within plantations are farming practices and surrounding landscape. Previous studies have shown that natural enemies are less abundant in plantations within simplified landscapes and intense management practices, while herbivores do not always respond to these factors. Given the different roles of arthropods in plantations, we assessed the cascading effects that the surrounding landscape and different management practices can have on different arthropod guilds in papaya plantations, ultimately affecting plant damage and fruit production. A piecewise structural equation model was used to assess the direct and indirect effects of management practices and landscape upon herbivores and their natural enemies, and their cascading effects on papaya leaf damage and fruit production. We studied 11 papaya plantations in the surroundings of a tropical dry forest (TDF) in Jalisco, Mexico. The model indicated that there is a decrease of natural enemies with intensive conventional management, which had no effect on pest abundance. Furthermore, surrounding landscape had an effect on pest abundance and not on predators, but this effect was different between seasons. Even when pest abundance explained crop damage, this was not reflected on fruit production. Crop yield was explained by management practices, available phosphorus in soil and by the abundance of natural enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
