<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Artículos on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Artículos on Estadística, modelación y manejo de datos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Economic valuation of ecosystem services from secondary tropical forests: trade-offs and implications for policy making</title>
      <link>/publication/naime-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/naime-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Natural regeneration of secondary forests can be an important source of recovery of ecosystem services (ES) critical for humanity, especially for climate change mitigation and adaptation goals. However, natural regeneration entails synergies and trade-offs across ESs and across stakeholders. To evaluate these trade-offs, we assessed the economic value of four ESs along the course of a natural regeneration process of tropical dry forests of the Pacific Coast of Mexico, and examined how this can inform the design of Payment for Ecosystem Services (PES) schemes incentivizing forest restoration. We estimated the monetary value of two provisioning ESs –forest products and fodder for calves–, using contingent valuation and direct market valuation methods, and two regulating ESs –carbon stocks and carbon sinks– using the voluntary carbon market prices and the social cost of carbon. We assessed these ESs in four natural regeneration stages: pasture, young secondary forest (0 to 12 years of natural regeneration), intermediate secondary forest (between 12 and 25 years of natural regeneration), and old-growth forest (more than 25 years of natural regeneration or primary forests).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling households’ natural resource management strategies: a case study in Jalisco, Mexico</title>
      <link>/publication/monroy-sais-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/monroy-sais-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The analysis of resource management strategies is considered to be relevant to the conservation and sustainable use of ecosystems. In Mexico, ejidos are the most important of the land tenure institutions that grant access to resources inside communities. Although it is recognized that an ejido’s internal structure creates different social groups, few studies have explored their resource management strategies. The aim of this study was to characterize natural resource management strategies in two ejidos in a highly biodiverse region on the southern coast of Jalisco, Mexico. We sought to identify differences in strategies and the variables that explain these differences. We took the household as the unit of analysis, and conducted 55 structured interviews that tackled different aspects of households’ productive activities and natural resource management. We used cluster and ordination analyses to generate a typology of natural resources management strategies, and linear models to identify the variables that differed among groups. The results show that four different natural resources management strategies were strongly associated with differences in land tenure and the type of ecosystem that a household manages. This information can help us to enhance and diversify strategies for sustaining both ecosystems and community livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the cascading effects of management and landscape on the arthropod guilds occurring in papaya plantations</title>
      <link>/publication/flores-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/flores-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arthropods can provide ecosystem services or disservices to agricultural systems. Whereas herbivores can cause substantial crop losses, natural enemies can offer pest regulation services that otherwise would be difficult to obtain. Two major factors affecting arthropod communities within plantations are farming practices and surrounding landscape. Previous studies have shown that natural enemies are less abundant in plantations within simplified landscapes and intense management practices, while herbivores do not always respond to these factors. Given the different roles of arthropods in plantations, we assessed the cascading effects that the surrounding landscape and different management practices can have on different arthropod guilds in papaya plantations, ultimately affecting plant damage and fruit production. A piecewise structural equation model was used to assess the direct and indirect effects of management practices and landscape upon herbivores and their natural enemies, and their cascading effects on papaya leaf damage and fruit production. We studied 11 papaya plantations in the surroundings of a tropical dry forest (TDF) in Jalisco, Mexico. The model indicated that there is a decrease of natural enemies with intensive conventional management, which had no effect on pest abundance. Furthermore, surrounding landscape had an effect on pest abundance and not on predators, but this effect was different between seasons. Even when pest abundance explained crop damage, this was not reflected on fruit production. Crop yield was explained by management practices, available phosphorus in soil and by the abundance of natural enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Susceptibility of Sphenarium purpurascens purpurascens (Orthoptera: Pyrgomorphidae) instars to a commercial strain of Metarhizium acridum (Hypocreales: Clavicipitaceae) in Michoacan, Mexico</title>
      <link>/publication/quesada-bejar-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/quesada-bejar-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el desempeño de una cepa comercial del hongo entomopatógeno Metarhizium acridum en diferentes estadios del saltamonte plaga Sphenarium purpurascens purpurascens, así como su esporulación a través de bioensayos bajo condiciones de laboratorio, en Michoacán, México. Los estadios más susceptibles fueron las ninfas uno, dos y cuatro, su tiempo de supervivencia promedio fue menor de 6,91 días. El menos susceptible fue el adulto, con un tiempo de supervivencia de 8,36 días. Los estadios con mayor esporulación post mortem fueron ninfas uno, dos y tres. Se registró una asociación negativa moderada entre los estadios de S. p. purpurascens y la esporulación de M. acridum, en estadios avanzados (ninfa 4 y adulto), en los cuales la esporulación fue menor en comparación con los estadios inmaduros. Todos los estadios mostraron tasas de supervivencia por debajo del 5 %, por lo tanto M. acridum se considera una opción viable para controlar esta plaga en el campo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resilience of soil aggregation and exocellular enzymatic functions associated with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal communities along a successional gradient in a tropical dry forest</title>
      <link>/publication/carrillo-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/carrillo-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi are well-known contributors to soil aggregation and nutrient cycling functions, but we still know little about their capacity to resist or recover from persistent disturbance. Rangeland management may deteriorate these functions by affecting the activity of soil biota, including AM fungi, among other consequences. If affected, some soil properties show recovery when management stops and natural regeneration is allowed. We conducted an experiment to evaluate if the functions related to soil aggregation and promotion of exocellular enzymatic activities associated with AM fungal communities had been affected by rangeland management and, if they had, whether they recovered with successional time when management stopped. AM fungal communities from ten sites with different successional ages in a tropical dry forest region were inoculated to the same host growing in pots divided by mesh into a plant compartment and an AM mycelium compartment. We examined soil stable aggregates fractions and enzymatic activities produced or promoted by AM fungi. Soil aggregation changed significantly only after the study had run for 3 years, was higher in the hyphosphere than in the root compartment, and showed a low but positive relation with the successional age of the communities. The activity of phosphatase, but not casein-protease and beta-glucosidase, increased with successional age. Therefore, soil aggregation and enzyme activities associated with AM fungal communities seemed resilient because casein-protease and beta-glucosidase were unchanged, and aggregation and phosphatase were reduced by rangeland management but recovered with successional time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local-scale spatial diversity patterns of ectomycorrhizal fungal communities in a subtropical pine-oak forest</title>
      <link>/publication/gavito-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gavito-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to analyze spatial patterns of soil ectomycorrhizal fungal (EMF) communities at the local scale in a subtropical pine-oak forest located in the Nearctic-Neotropical transition in central Mexico, to underpin biodiversity conservation strategies in forest fragments of this region. We used a spatially-explicit nested square sampling design with the same sampling representativeness at all scales and replicated three times. We detected 674 EMF OTUs within 19,200m2 and 65 OTUs on average per sample. Seventy percent of OTUs were detected in only 1e4 samples. Average community similarity was below 5%, showed minor change within 14 and 339m distance and increased with the spatial grain used to compare the data. We found a high species-area relationship and beta diversity coefficients for soil fungi indicating that, at the local scale, increasing area by a constant factor of four represented an in- crease in OTU richness by a factor of two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The spatial analysis of biological interactions: morphological variation responding to the co‐occurrence of competitors and resources</title>
      <link>/publication/tovilla-sierra-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/tovilla-sierra-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By sharing geographic space, species are forced to interact with one another and the contribution of this process to evolutionary and ecological patterns of individual spe- cies is not fully understood. At the same time, species turnover makes that species composition varies from one area to another, so the analysis of biological interaction cannot be uncoupled from the spatial context. This is particularly important for clades that show high degree of specialization such as hummingbirds, where any variation in biotic pressures might lead to changes in morphology. Here, we describe the influence of biological interactions on the morphology of Hylocharis leucotis by simultaneously considering potential competition and diet resources. We characterized the extent of local potential competition and local available floral resources by correlating two mea- surements of hummingbird diversity, floral resources and the size of morphological space of H. leucotis along its geographic distribution. We found that H. leucotis shows an important morphological variability across its range and two groups can be recog- nized. Surprisingly, morphological variation is not always linked to local hummingbird richness or the phylogenetic similarity of. Only in the southern part of its distribution, H. leucotis is morphologically more variable in those communities where it coexist with closely related hummingbird species. We also found that morphological variation in H. leucotis is independent from the availability of floral resources. Our results suggest that abiotic factors might be responsible for morphological differences across popula- tions in Hylocharis leucotis being biological interactions of minor importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alterations in honey bee gut microorganisms caused by Nosema spp. and pest control methods</title>
      <link>/publication/diaz-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/diaz-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Honey bees are associated with gut microorganisms essential for their nutrition and health. The composition of the microbial community can be used as a biological health indicator and is characterized using biomarker fatty acids. Commonly, gut microorganisms are exposed to pathogens and to an array of chemical and biological pest control methods. 
RESULTS: We found a strong negative effect on microbial gut community composition when exposed to the bee pest control chemicals oxytetracycline, oxalic acid and imidacloprid, and when inoculated with the bee pest Nosema spp. and the potential bee pest biocontrol agent Lactobacillus plantarum. Results from the in vitro test with bee pest chemicals showed a differential response of Lactobacillus spp. At the community level, sometaxonomicgroupsweremoreaffecteddependingon treatment, but sharp changes in the microbial structure were caused by compounds generally considered as bee safe. 
CONCLUSION: Our results show that pests such as Nosema spp. and pest control methods alter the composition of bee gut microorganisms, which may have severe consequences for pathogen defense, physiology and general honey bee health. In addition, L. plantarum has potential as a biocontrol agent against Nosema spp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plant growth promotion traits of rhizosphere yeasts and their response to soil characteristics and crop cycle in maize agroecosystems</title>
      <link>/publication/sarabia-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/sarabia-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yeasts are common soil inhabitants, but information about their ecology is limited. Here we examined the abundance of rhizosphere yeasts in six conventional maize agroecosystems in two different geographic areas in Mexico differing in soil characteristics and agricultural practices. In order to examine the plant growth promotion potential of maize rhizosphere yeasts a collection of yeast species was obtained, which were identified taxonomically in terms of sequencing of the D1D2 domain. Main results showed that yeasts were present in all maize fields during the complete growing cycle, though highest during flowering. The abundance of rhizosphere yeasts responded negatively to soil pH and amount of Mg. The maize rhizosphere yeast collection obtained included eight species from six genera with the Ascomycota species Meyerozyma guillermondii and Candida railenensis as the most frequent. Four out of the eight yeast species solubilised Ca3(PO4)2, whereas none of the yeasts solubilised FePO4. Maize plant growth was promoted after inoculation with Cryptococcus flavus and Solicoccozyma aeria in terms of shoot dry weight and with C. railenensis in terms of root dry weight, but only in combination with mineral P fertilisation. In conclusion, rhizosphere yeasts with plant growth promotion traits are common in maize agroecosystems, where soil physico-chemical characteristics and plant growth stage seem to determine their abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal spore communities of a tropical dry forest ecosystem show resilience to land-use change</title>
      <link>/publication/carrillo-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/carrillo-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We explored the resilience of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal (AMF) communities of a tropical dry forest ecosystem to land use as pastures. We compared spore community species richness, composition, abundance, and similarity between old-growth forests and active pastures, as a measure of resistance and examined the trajectory of change in successional fields when pasture use stopped to evaluate re- covery. Despite a few changes in species richness, community composition and structure were strikingly similar in all sites, including the active pastures. The spore communities were considered resistant to land use as pastures and showed minor changes along succession when management stopped. We found a significant negative relation between the frequency of Diversisporales and Glomerales indicating a selective species turnover driven mainly by the families Gigasporaceae and Glomeraceae. This was, however, unrelated to land use or successional time. These results suggest the AMF communities of this ecosystem seem resilient to management as pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sociability between invasive guppies and native topminnows</title>
      <link>/publication/camacho-cervantes-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/camacho-cervantes-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We explored the resilience of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal (AMF) communities of a tropical dry forest ecosystem to land use as pastures. We compared spore community species richness, composition, abundance, and similarity between old-growth forests and active pastures, as a measure of resistance and examined the trajectory of change in successional fields when pasture use stopped to evaluate re- covery. Despite a few changes in species richness, community composition and structure were strikingly similar in all sites, including the active pastures. The spore communities were considered resistant to land use as pastures and showed minor changes along succession when management stopped. We found a significant negative relation between the frequency of Diversisporales and Glomerales indicating a selective species turnover driven mainly by the families Gigasporaceae and Glomeraceae. This was, however, unrelated to land use or successional time. These results suggest the AMF communities of this ecosystem seem resilient to management as pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ortópteros ( Caelifera ) y sus hongos entomopatógenos en agroecosistemas de maíz en Erongarícuaro , Michoacán</title>
      <link>/publication/quesada-bejar-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/quesada-bejar-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Los saltamontes son una plaga importante del maíz, uno de sus enemigos naturales son los hongos entomopatógenos (HEP). El manejo adecuado de este cultivo, que involucre cambios en el microhábitat puede contribuir al control de las poblaciones de saltamontes, así como la presencia de sus enemigos naturales. Se evaluó el efecto de dos tipos de manejo agrícola: monocultivo (MC-I) de maíz y policultivo de maíz, calabaza y frijol (PC-I), así como de la vegetación de los márgenes del monocultivo (VMM) y la vegetación de los márgenes del policultivo (VMP), sobre la riqueza y abundancia de saltamontes y sus hongos entomopatógenos (HEP) asociados en Erongarícuaro, Michoacán. Se recolectaron saltamontes mensualmente con una red de golpeo de julio a diciembre de 2015 en dos parcelas de cada tipo de manejo y su vegetación marginal en tres sitios. La comunidad de saltamontes (CS) estuvo conformada por 17 especies, en donde Sphenarium purpurascens purpurascens Charpentier, fue la especie dominante (97.8% de la abundancia). El tipo de manejo agrícola no tuvo efecto sobre la riqueza de especies. La riqueza en la vegetación marginal de los cultivos no explicó la riqueza en el MC-I y PC-I; sin embargo, la abundancia de S. p. purpurascens en la vegetación marginal en los sitios explicó la abundancia encontrada en el MC-I y el PC-I. De 2 920 saltamontes colectados, 0.41% estuvieron infectados por Metarhizium Sorokin o Beauveria (Balsamo) Vuillemin. El HEP con mayor frecuencia de infección fue Metarhizium. La proporción de individuos infectados y las condiciones del PC-I se relacionaron positivamente, en comparación con la VMP. Los sitios con mayor diversidad vegetal tuvieron una mayor abundancia de saltamontes y mayor infección con HEP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Precipitation mediates the effect of human disturbance on the Brazilian Caatinga vegetation</title>
      <link>/publication/rito-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/rito-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*Seasonally dry tropical forests (SDTFs) are one of the most threatened forests worldwide. These species-rich forests not only cope with several acute (e.g. forest loss) and chronic (e.g. overgrazing and firewood extraction) human disturbances, but also with climate change (e.g. longer and more severe droughts); yet, the isolated and combined effects of climate and acute and chronic human disturbances on SDTF vegetation are poorly known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the environmental filter imposed by drought in SDTFs, the composition and structure of vegetation is expected to be strongly associated with annual precipitation, and thus the effects of human disturbances on vegetation may also depend on precipitation (i.e. interacting effect).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We tested these hypotheses in the Brazilian Caatinga – a SDTF threatened by climate change and human disturbances. We evaluated the isolated and combined (both additive and multiplicative) effect of precipitation, a chronic disturbance index and acute disturbance (landscape forest cover) on the diversity, stem density, evenness, taxonomic composition and aboveground biomass of adult trees and shrubs across 19 0.1-ha plots distributed along a disturbance and precipitation gradients. * We recorded 5541 stems from 129 species. Precipitation showed a stronger (positive) effect on species diversity than acute and chronic disturbances and, as expected, the effect of disturbance depended on precipitation (interacting effect): i.e. species diversity (especially the number of rare species) was negatively related to forest loss but positively related to chronic disturbance in wetter sites, whereas in drier sites, species diversity was weakly related to forest cover, but strongly and negatively related to chronic disturbance. Contrary to species diversity, community evenness, stem density and biomass were weakly related to all predictors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synthesis. Precipitation appears to be a strong environmental filter determining the distribution of water-demanding plant species. Chronic disturbance in wetter (high-productive) forests may favour species diversity by increasing ecosystem heterogeneity (intermediate disturbance hypothesis). Yet, the biodiversity costs of chronic disturbance are higher in drier (low-productive) forests; i.e. there is a co-limitation imposed by drought and disturbance in drier forests. Overall, our findings indicate that rapid climatic changes in the region will probably have strong negative effects on this SDTF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizontal seed dispersal by dung beetles reduced seed and seedling clumping, but did not increase short-term seedling establishment</title>
      <link>/publication/urrea-galeano-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/urrea-galeano-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dung beetles are secondary seed dispersers, incidentally moving many of the seeds defecated by mammals vertically (seed burial) and/or horizontally as they process and relocate dung. Although several studies have quantified this ecological function of dung beetles, very few have followed seed fate until seedling establishment, and most of these have focused on the effects of seed burial. We know very little about the effects of horizontal seed movement by dung beetles, though it is generally assumed that it will affect plant recruitment positively through diminishing seed clumping. The objective of our study was to assess the effects of dung beetle activity on the spatial distribution of seeds and seedlings, and on the probability of seedling establishment. In a tropical rainforest in Mexico we carried out two complementary field experiments for each of two tree species (Bursera simaruba and Poulsenia armata), using seeds experimentally imbedded in pig dung and recording their fate and spatial location over time. For both species, dung beetle activity reduced the spatial clumping of seeds and seedlings; however, it did not increase the probability of seedling establishment. We discuss the context- and species-specificity of the combined effects of horizontal and vertical dispersal of seeds by dung beetles, and the need to quantify long-term seedling fates to more accurately determine the effects of seed movement by dung beetles on plant recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
